Pygmalion, by me, George Bernard Shaw, Episode 2.
Eliza has not passed as a Duchess yet, and Higgins's bet remains on one.
But the six months are not yet exhausted, and just in time, Eliza does actually pass
as a Princess.
For a glimpse of how she did it, imagine an embassy in London, one summer evening, after
dark.
A grand reception is in progress.
A small crowd is lined up to see the guests arrive.
A Rolls-Royce car drives up.
Colonel Pickering, in evening dress, with medals and orders, alights.
And hands out Eliza, in opera cloak, evening dress, diamonds, fan, flowers and all accessories.
Higgins follows.
The car drives off, and the three go up the steps and into the house, the door opening
for them as they approach.
One of the guests is an important-looking young man, with an astonishingly hairy face.
Maestro!
Ah, Professor Higgins!
Mwah!
Do you remember me?
No, I don't.
Who the devil are you?
I am your pupil, your first pupil, your best and greatest pupil.
I am little Nepomuk, the marvellous boy.
I have made your name famous throughout Europe.
You teach me phonetic.
You cannot forget me.
Do you know Colonel Pickering, the author of spoken Sanskrit?
Good evening.
Why don't you shave?
Well, I have not your impulsing appearance, your chin, your brow.
Nobody noticed me when I shaved.
Now I am famous.
They call me hairy-faced dick.
And what are you doing here among all these swells?
I am interpreter.
I speak thirty-two languages.
I am indispensable at these international parties.
You are great cockney specialist.
You place a man anywhere in London the moment he opens his mouth.
I place a man in Europe.
You are wanted upstairs.
Her Excellency cannot understand the Greek, gentlemen.
Thank you.
Yes.
Immediately.
This Greek diplomatist pretends he cannot speak or understand English.
He cannot deceive me.
He is a son of a Clerkenwell watchmaker.
He speaks English so villainously that he dare not utter a word of it without betraying
his origin.
I help him to pretend, but I make him pay through the nose.
I make them all pay.
Is this fellow really an expert?
Can he find out Eliza and blackmail her?
We shall see.
If he finds her out, I lose my bet.
Ah, Eliza.
Now for it.
Are you ready?
Are you nervous, Colonel?
Frightfully.
I feel exactly as I felt before my first battle.
It's the first time that frightens.
It is not the first time for me, Colonel.
I have done this fifty times, hundreds of times, in my little pickery in Angel Court
in my daydreams.
I am in a dream now.
Promise me not to let Professor Higgins wake me.
For if he does, I shall forget everything and talk as I used to Drury Lane.
Not a word, Higgins.
Now, ready?
Ready.
Go.
Miss Doolittle, Colonel Pickering, Professor Higgins.
How do you do?
How do you do, Pickering?
Is that your adopted daughter, Colonel Pickering?
She will make a sensation.
Most kind of you to invite her.
Nipamuk, find out all about her.
Excellent.
In the drawing room, the reception is in full swing.
Eliza passes through.
She is so intent on her ordeal that she walks like a somnambulist in a desert
instead of a debutante in a fashionable crowd.
They stop talking to look at her.
Eliza is a sensation.
Not a hint of nervousness.
Ah, there is Professor Higgins.
He will tell us.
Tell us about the wonderful young lady, Professor.
What wonderful young lady?
You know very well.
Tell me, there has been nothing like her in London
since people stood on their chairs to look at Mrs. Liontree.
Ah, there you are at last, Nipamuk.
Have you found out all about the Doolittle lady?
I have found out all about her.
She is a fraud.
A fraud?
Oh, no.
Yes, yes.
She cannot deceive me.
Her name cannot be Doolittle.
Why?
Because Doolittle is an English name and she is not English.
Nonsense.
She speaks English perfectly.
Too perfectly.
Can you show me any Englishwoman who speaks English as it should be spoken?
Only foreigners who have been taught to speak it, speak it well.
Certainly she terrified me by the way she said, how do you do?
I had a schoolmistress who talked like that and I was mortally afraid of her.
But if she is not English, what is she?
Hungarian.
I get it.
Hungarian and of royal blood.
I am Hungarian.
My blood is royal.
Did you speak to her in Hungarian?
I did.
She was very clever.
She said, please speak to me in English.
I do not understand French.
Oh, French.
She pretends not to know the difference between Hungarian and French.
Impossible.
She knows both.
And the royal blood, how did you find that out?
Instinct, Mastro, instinct.
Only the Magyar races can produce that air of the divine right.
Those resolute eyes.
She is a princess.
What do you say, Professor?
I say, an ordinary London girl out of the gutter and taught to speak by an expert.
I place her in Drury Lane.
Oh, Mastro, Mastro.
You are mad on the subject of Cockney dialects.
The London gutter is the whole world for you.
What does Your Excellency say?
Oh, of course I agree with Neptune.
She must be a princess at least.
Not necessarily legitimate, of course, but that is undoubtedly her class.
I stick to my opinion.
You are incorrigible.
Where is Eliza?
You must keep an eye on her.
I don't think I can bear much more.
The people all stare so at me.
An old lady has just told me that I speak exactly like Queen Victoria.
I am sorry if I have lost your bet.
I have done my best, but nothing can make me the same as these people.
You have not lost it, my dear.
You have won it ten times over.
I've had enough of chattering to these fools.
Eliza is tired and I am hungry.
Let us clear out and have supper somewhere.
I say, pick lock up, will you?
Right.
Can Mrs Pearce go to bed?
We don't want anything more, do we?
Oh, no.
I say, Mrs Pearce will row if we leave our coats lying about in the drawing room.
Chuck them over the banisters into the hall.
She'll find them there in the morning and put them away all right.
She'll think we were drunk.
We are, most likely.
Are there any letters?
I didn't look.
I wonder where the devil my slippers are?
Only circulars and this coroneted billet do for you.
Oh, yeah, money lender.
Oh, Lord, what an evening.
What a crew.
Silly tomfoolery.
Oh, here are my slippers.
Look.
Oh, I feel a bit tired.
It's been a long day.
The garden party, dinner party and the opera.
Not too much of a good thing.
But you've won your bet, Higgins.
Eliza did the trick and something to spare.
Thank God it's over.
Were you nervous at the garden party?
I was.
Eliza didn't seem a bit nervous.
No, she wasn't nervous.
I've had a routine of putting the job through
all these months that has told on me.
It was interesting enough at first
while we were at the phonetics.
But after that, I got deadly sick of it.
If I hadn't backed myself to do it,
I should have chucked the whole thing up two months ago.
It was a silly notion.
The whole thing had been a bore.
Oh, come.
The garden party was frightfully exciting.
My heart began beating like anything.
Well, yes, for the first three minutes.
But when I saw we were going to win hands down,
sitting in a cage, hanging about, doing nothing,
the dinner was worse.
Sitting gorging there for over an hour
with nobody but a damn fool
of a fashionable woman to talk to.
I tell you, Pickering,
never again for me.
No more artificial duchesses.
The whole thing has been simple perpetrate.
Well, you've never been broken in properly
to the social routine.
I rather enjoy dipping into it occasionally myself.
Makes me feel young again.
Anyhow, it was a great success,
an immense success.
I was quite frightened once or twice
because Eliza was doing it so well.
You see, lots of the real people can't do it at all.
They're such fools that they think
style comes by nature to people in their position,
and so they never learn.
There's always something professional
about doing a thing superlatively well.
Yes.
That's what drives me mad.
Silly people don't know their own silly business.
However,
it's over and done with,
and I can go to bed at last without dreading tomorrow.
Yes, I think I shall turn in too.
Still, it's been a great occasion,
a triumph for you.
Good night.
Oh, put out the lights.
And tell Mrs. Pierce
not to make coffee for me in the morning.
I'll take D.
What the devil have I done with my slippers?
There are your slippers.
And there.
Take your slippers and make you never have a day's luck with them.
What on earth?
What's the matter?
Anything wrong?
Nothing wrong with you.
I've won your bet for you, haven't I?
That's enough for you.
I don't matter, I suppose.
You won my bet?
You presumptuous insect.
I won it.
What did you throw those slippers at me for?
I wanted to smash your face.
I'd like to kill you, you selfish brute.
Why didn't you leave me where you picked me out of,
in the gutter?
You thank God it's all over,
and that now you can throw me back again there, do you?
The creature is nervous after all.
Get up.
Would you?
Crawl in, you cat.
How dare you show your temper to me?
Sit down and be quiet.
What's to become of me?
How the devil do I know what's to become of you?
What does it matter what becomes of you?
You don't care.
I know you don't care.
You wouldn't care if I was dead.
I am nothing to you.
Not so much as them slippers.
Those slippers!
Those slippers.
I didn't think it made any difference now.
Why have you begun
going on like this?
May I ask
whether you complain of your treatment here?
No.
Has anybody behaved badly to you?
Colonel Pickering?
Mrs. Pierce?
Any of the servants?
No.
I presume you don't pretend that I have treated you badly?
I am glad to hear it.
Perhaps you're tired after the strain of the day.
Will you have a glass of champagne?
No!
Thank you.
This has been coming on you
for some days.
I suppose it was natural
for you to be anxious
about the garden party
but that's all over now.
There's nothing more to worry about.
No.
Nothing more for you to worry about.
Oh God,
I wish I was dead!
Why?
In heaven's name, why?
Listen to me, Eliza.
All this irritation is purely subjective.
I don't understand!
I'm too ignorant!
It's only imagination.
Low spirits
and nothing else.
Nobody's hurting you.
Nothing's wrong.
You go to bed like a good girl
and sleep it off.
That will make you comfortable.
I heard your prayers.
Thank God it's all over!
Don't you thank God it's all over?
Now you are free
and can do what you like.
What am I fit for?
What have you left me fit for?
Where am I to go?
What am I to do?
What's to become of me?
That's what's worrying you, eh?
I shouldn't bother about it
if I were you.
I should imagine you won't have much difficulty
in settling yourself somewhere.
I hadn't quite realised
that you were going away.
You might marry.
You see,
all men are not confirmed old bachelors
like me and the Colonel.
Most men are the marrying sort.
Poor devils.
And you're not bad looking.
It's a pleasure to look at you sometimes.
Not now, of course,
because you're crying and looking as ugly
as a very devil.
But when you're alright
and yourself,
you're what I should call
attractive,
that is to the people
in the marrying line,
you go to bed,
have a nice good rest
and then get up
and look at yourself in the glass
and say,
I'm not a bad chap or other
who would do very well.
We're above that at the corner
of Tottenham Court Road.
What do you mean?
I sold flowers.
I didn't sell myself.
Now you've made a lady of me,
I'm not fit to sell anything else.
I wish you'd left me where you found me.
Tosh, Eliza!
Don't you insult human relations
by dragging all this cant about
What about your old idea
of a florist shop?
Pickering could set you up in one.
He's lots of money.
He'll have to pay for all those togs you've been wearing today.
And that, with the hire of the jewellery,
will make a big hole in £200.
Why?
Six months ago,
you would have thought it the millennium
to have a flower shop of your own.
Come,
you'll be alright.
I must clear off to bed.
I'm terribly sleepy.
By the way, I came down for something.
I forget what it was.
Your slippers.
Oh, yes, of course.
You shied them at me.
Before you go, sir.
Huh?
Do my clothes
belong to me or to Colonel Pickering?
What the devil
use would they be to Pickering?
He might want them for the next girl
you pick up to experiment on.
Is that the way you feel towards us?
I don't want to hear anything more about it.
All I want to know
is whether anything belongs to me.
My own clothes were burnt.
But what does it matter?
Why need you start bothering about that
in the middle of the night?
I want to know
what I may take away with me.
I don't want to be accused of stealing.
Stealing?
Oh, no,
you shouldn't have said that, Eliza.
That shows a want of feeling.
I'm sorry.
I'm only a common, ignorant girl.
And in my station, I have to be careful.
There can't be any feelings
between the like of you and the like of me.
Please will you tell me
what belongs to me and what doesn't?
Oh, you may take the whole damned house full
if you like.
Except the jewels. They're hired.
Will that satisfy you?
Stop, please.
Will you take these to your room
and keep them safe?
I don't want to run the risk of their being missing.
Hand them over!
If these belonged to me
instead of to the jeweler,
I'd ram them down your ungrateful throat.
This ring isn't the jeweler's.
It's the one you bought me in Brighton.
I don't want it now.
Oh, you infamous creature.
Don't you hit me!
Hit you?
How dare you accuse me of such a thing?
You've hit me.
You have wounded me to the heart.
I'm glad.
I've got a little of my own back, anyhow.
You have caused me
to lose my temper.
A thing that has hardly ever
happened to me before.
I prefer to say nothing more tonight.
I am going to bed.
We had better leave a note
for Mrs. Pierce about the coffee.
For she won't be told
by me.
Damn Mrs. Pierce
and damn the coffee
and damn you
and damn my own folly
for having lavished
my hard-earned knowledge
and the treasure
of my regard
and intimacy
on a heartless guttersnipe.
Mmm.
Freddy!
What are you doing here?
Nothing.
I spend most of my nights here
gazing up at your window.
It's the only place where I'm happy.
Don't laugh at me, Miss Doolittle.
Do you hear?
Lies is good enough for me.
Freddy.
You don't think I'm a heartless guttersnipe, do you?
Oh, no.
Darling, how can you imagine such a thing?
You...
You are the loveliest, dearest...
Oh!
Mmm.
Marvin! Marvin!
Sorry, Constable.
We've only just become engaged.
Double quick.
You didn't half give me a fight, that copper.
But you answered him proper.
I had no idea the police were so devilishly prudish.
It's their business
to hunt girls off the streets.
I hope I haven't taken you out of your way.
Where were you going?
To the river.
What for?
To make a hole in it.
Eliza, darling, what do you mean?
I don't know.
There's nobody in the world now,
but you and me is there.
Not a soul.
Look, we must go somewhere.
We can't wander about the streets all night.
Can't we?
I think it'd be lovely to wander about forever.
Oh, darling.
Can I drive you and the lady
anywhere, sir?
Oh, Freddy, a taxi.
The very thing.
But dammit, I've no money.
I have plenty.
The Colonel thinks you should never go out
without ten pounds in your pocket.
Listen, we'll drive about all night,
and in the morning, I'll call old Mrs. Higgins
and ask her what I ought to do.
I'll tell you all about it in the cab.
Right-o. A ripping.
Wimbledon Common.
MUSIC
Mr. Henry, ma'am, is downstairs
with Colonel Pickering.
Well, show them up.
They're using the telephone, ma'am.
Telephoning to the police, I think.
What?
Mr. Henry's in a state, ma'am.
If you'd told me that Mr. Henry was not in a state,
it would have been more surprising.
Tell them to come up when they've finished
with the police.
I suppose he's lost something.
Yes, ma'am.
Go upstairs and tell Miss Doolittle
that Mr. Henry and the Colonel are here.
Ask her not to come down
till I send for her.
Yes, ma'am.
Look, young mother,
here's a confounded thing.
Yes, dear.
What is it?
Eliza's bolted.
You must have frightened her.
Frightened her? Nonsense.
She was left last night as usual
to turn out the lights and all that
and instead of going to bed
she changed her clothes and went right off.
Her bed wasn't slept in.
She came in a cab for her things
before seven this morning
and that fool Mrs. Pearce let her have them
without telling me a word about it.
What am I to do?
With all the appointments I've got
I'm absolutely lost, Mrs. Higgins.
Has Henry told you?
What does that ass of an inspector say?
Have you offered a reward?
You don't need to say that you set the police
after Eliza.
Of course. What are the police for?
What else could we do?
The inspector made a lot of difficulties.
I really think he suspected us
of some improper purpose.
Of course he did.
What right have you to go to the police
But we want to find her.
We can't let her go like this, you know, Mrs. Higgins.
What are we to do?
You have no more sense, either of you,
than two children.
Mr. Henry, a gentleman wants to see you
very particular.
He's been sent on from Wimpole Street.
I can't see anyone now. Who is it?
Mr. Doolittle, sir.
Doolittle? Do you mean the dustman?
Dustman? No, sir. A gentleman.
By George Pick!
It's some relative of hers that she's gone to.
A relative we know nothing about.
Send him up, quick!
Yes, sir.
Gentile relatives?
Now we shall hear some things.
Do you know any of her people?
Only her father, the fellow we told you about.
Mr. Doolittle.
See here? Do you see this?
You done this?
Done what, man?
This, I tell you. Look at it.
Look at this silk hat. Look at this frock coat.
These shoes.
Why would she buy me clothes?
Good morning, Mr. Doolittle.
Won't you sit down?
Asking your pardon, ma'am.
Thank you.
I'm that full of what has happened to me
that I can't think of anything else.
What the dickens has happened to you?
I shouldn't mind if it had only happened to me.
Anything might happen to anybody
and nobody to blame but Providence, as you might say.
But this is something you
have done to me.
Yes, you, Henry Higgins.
You found Eliza.
Have you lost her?
Yes.
You have all the luck you have.
I ain't found her but she'll find me
quick enough now after what you have done to me.
But what has my son done to you, Mr. Doolittle?
Done to me? Ruined me.
Destroyed my happiness.
Tied me up and delivered me
into the hands of middle class morality.
You're raving.
You're drunk.
You're mad.
Drunk, am I?
Murder, am I?
Tell me this.
Did you or did you not
write a letter to an old blighter in America
that was giving five millions
to found moral reform societies
all over the world and that wanted you
to invent a universal language for him?
What? Ezra D. Wannafella?
He's dead.
Yes, he's dead.
And I'm done for.
Now, did you or did you not
expect to him to say that the most original moralist
at present in England, to the best of your knowledge,
was Alfred Doolittle,
a common dustman?
Oh. Well, after your last visit,
I remember making some silly joke of the kind.
Oh.
You may well call it
a silly joke.
It put the lid on me right enough.
Just give him the chance he wanted
to show that Americans is not like us.
That they recognize and respect merit
in every class of life, however humble.
Them words is in his blooming will
in which, Henry Higgins,
thanks to your silly joking,
he leaves me a share in his pre-digested
cheese trust worth 3,000 a year
on condition that I lecture
for his Wannafella Moral Reform World League
as often as they ask me.
Up to six times a year.
That definitely does. Oh, what a lark.
A safe thing for you, Doolittle.
They won't ask you twice.
It ain't the lecture in my mind.
I'll lecture them blue in the face I will
and not turn an ear.
It's making a gentleman of me that I object to.
Who asked him to make a gentleman of me?
I was happy.
I was free.
I touched pretty nigh everybody
for money when I wanted it.
Same as I touched you, Henry Higgins.
Now I am worried
tied neck and heels
and everybody touches me for money.
When I was a poor man
the doctors used to shove me out of the hospital
before I could hardly stand on my legs
and I had nothing to pay.
Now they find out that I'm not a healthy man
and can't live unless they looks after me twice a day.
In the house, I'm not let to do
an hand's turn for meself.
Somebody else must do it
and touch me for it.
A year ago, I hadn't a relative in the world
except two or three that wouldn't speak to me.
Now I have 50
and not a decent week's wages among a lot of them.
I have to live for others
and not for meself.
That's middle class morality.
Don't you be anxious.
I bet she's on my doorstep by this.
She that could support herself easy
by selling flowers if I wasn't respectable.
And the next one to touch me
will be you.
Henry Higgins, I'll have to learn
to speak middle class language from you
instead of speaking proper English.
That's where you'll come in
and I dare say
that's what you've done it for.
But my dear Mr Doolittle
you need not suffer all this
if you're really in earnest.
Nobody can force you to accept this bequest.
You can repudiate it.
Isn't that so, Colonel Pickering?
I believe so.
That's the tragedy of it, ma'am.
It's easy to say chuck it
but I haven't the nerve.
Which one of us has?
We're all intimidated.
Intimidated, ma'am.
That's what we are.
What is there for me if I chuck it
but the workhouse in my old age?
If I was one of the deserving poor
and had put by a bit
I could chuck it
but then why should I?
Because the deserving poor might as well be millionaires
for all the happiness they ever have.
They don't know what happiness is.
But I, as one of the undeserving poor
have nothing between me and a pauper's uniform
but this here blasted
three thousand a year
that shoves me into the middle class.
Excuse the expression, ma'am.
You'd use it yourself if you had my provocation.
They've got you every way you turn.
Intimidated.
That's what I am.
Broke. Bought up.
Happier men than me will call for my dust
and touch me for their tip.
And I'll look on, helpless, and envied of them, and that, that's what your son has brought me to.
Well, I'm very glad you're not going to do anything foolish, Mr Doolittle.
But this solves the problem of Eliza's future. You can provide for her now.
Yes, Mum. I'm expected to provide for everyone now, out of 3,000 a year.
Nonsense. He can't provide for her. He shan't provide for her. She doesn't belong to him.
I paid him five pounds for her. Doolittle, either you're an honest man or a rogue.
A little of both, Henry, like the rest of us. A little of both.
But you took that money for the girl, and you've no rights to take her as well.
Henry, don't be absurd. If you really want to know where Eliza is, she's upstairs.
Upstairs? Well, then I shall jolly soon fetch her downstairs.
Be quiet, Henry. Sit down.
I?
Sit down, dear, and listen to me.
Oh, very well, very well, very well. But I think you might have told us this half an hour ago.
Eliza came to me this morning. She told me of the brutal way you two treated her.
What?
My dear Mrs Higgins, she's been telling you stories. We didn't treat her brutally.
Brutally? We hardly said a word to her, and we parted on particularly good terms.
Higgins, did you bully her after I went to bed?
Just the other way about. She threw my slippers in my face.
She behaved in the most outrageous way. I never gave her the slightest provocation.
The slippers came bang into my face the moment I entered the room,
before I had uttered a word and used perfectly awful language.
But why? What did we do to her?
I think I know pretty well what you did.
The girl is naturally rather affectionate, I think. Isn't she, Mr Doolittle?
Very tender-hearted, ma'am. Takes after me.
Just so. She had become attached to you both.
She worked very hard for you, Henry.
I don't think you quite realise what anything in the nature of brain work means to a girl like that.
Well, it seems to me that when the great day of trial came,
and she did this wonderful thing for you without making a single mistake,
you two sat there and never said a word to her,
but talked together of how glad you were that it was all over,
and how you'd been bored with the whole thing.
And then you were surprised because she threw your slippers at you.
I should have thrown the fire irons at you.
We said nothing except that we were tired and wanted to go to bed. Did we, Peg?
That was all.
Quite sure?
Absolutely. Really, that was all.
You didn't thank her, or pet her, or admire her, or tell her how splendid she'd been.
But she knew all about that. We didn't make speeches to her, if that's what you mean.
Perhaps we were a little inconsiderate.
Is she very angry?
I'm afraid she won't go back to Wimpole Street,
especially now that Mr Doolittle is able to keep up the position that you thrust upon her.
But she says she's quite willing to meet you on friendly terms and let bygones be bygones.
Is she, bright George?
If you promise to behave yourself, Henry, I'll ask her to come down.
If not, go home, for you've taken up quite enough of my time.
All right. Very well.
Peg, you behave yourself.
Let us put on our best Sunday manners for this creature that we picked out of the mud.
Now, now, Henry Higgins. Have some consideration for my feelings as a middle-class man.
Remember your promise, Henry.
Mr Doolittle, will you be good enough as to step out on the balcony for a moment?
I don't want Eliza to have the shock of your news until she's made it up with these two gentlemen.
Would you mind?
As you wish, lady. Anything to help Henry keep her off my hands.
Ask Miss Doolittle to come down, please.
Yes, ma'am.
Now, Henry, be good.
I am behaving myself perfectly.
He is doing his best, Mrs Higgins.
Henry, dearest, you don't look at all nice in that attitude.
I was not trying to look nice, Mother.
It doesn't matter, dear. I only wanted to make you speak.
Why?
Because you can't speak and whistle at the same time.
Oh, the devil is that girl.
Are we to wait here all day?
How do you do, Professor Higgins?
Are you comfortable?
Are you quite well?
Am I?
But of course you are. You are never ill.
So glad to see you again, Colonel Pickering.
Quite chilly this morning, isn't it?
Don't you dare try this game on me.
I taught it to you and it doesn't take me in.
Get up and come home and don't be a fool.
Very nicely put indeed, Henry.
No woman could resist such an invitation.
Do let her alone, Mother. Let her speak for herself.
You will jolly soon see whether she has an idea that I haven't put into her head
or a word that I haven't put into her mouth.
I tell you, I have created this thing
out of the squashed cabbage leaves of Covent Garden
and now she pretends to play the fine lady with me.
Yes, dear, but you'll sit down, won't you?
Will you drop me altogether now that the experiment is over, Colonel Pickering?
Oh, don't. You mustn't think of it as an experiment.
It shocks me somehow.
Oh, I'm only a squashed cabbage leaf.
No.
But I owe so much to you that I should be very unhappy if you forgot me.
It's very kind of you to say so, Miss Doolittle.
It's not because you paid for my dresses.
I know you are generous to everybody with money
but it was from you that I learnt really nice manners
and that is what makes one a lady, isn't it?
You see, it was so very difficult for me
with the example of Professor Higgins always before me.
I was brought up to be just like him.
Unable to control myself
and using bad language on the slightest provocation.
And I should never have known that ladies and gentlemen
didn't behave like that if you hadn't been there.
He taught you to speak and I couldn't have done that, you know.
Of course, that is his profession.
Damnation, Henry!
It was just like learning to dance in the fashionable way.
There is nothing more than that in it.
But do you know what began my real education?
What?
Your calling me Miss Doolittle that day when I first came to Wimpole Street.
That was the beginning of self-respect for me.
And there were a hundred little things you never noticed
because they came naturally to you.
Things about standing up and taking off your hat and opening doors.
Oh, that was nothing.
Yes, things that showed you thought and felt about me
as if I was something better than a scullery maid.
Though, of course, I know you would have been just the same to a scullery maid
if she had been let in the drawing room.
You never took off your boots in the dining room when I was there.
Oh, you mustn't mind that.
Higgins takes off his boots all over the place.
I know. I'm not blaming him.
It is his way, isn't it?
But it made such a difference to me that you didn't do it.
You see, really and truly, apart from the things anyone could pick up
the dressing and the proper way of speaking and so on
the difference between a lady and a flower girl
is not how she behaves but how she is treated.
I shall always be a flower girl to Professor Higgins
because he always treats me as a flower girl and always will.
But I know I can be a lady to you
because you always treat me as a lady and always will.
Please don't grind your teeth, Henry.
Well, this is really very nice of you, Miss Doolittle.
I should like you to call me Eliza now, if you would.
Oh, thank you. Eliza, of course.
And I should like Professor Higgins to call me Miss Doolittle.
I'll see you damned first!
Henry, Henry.
Why don't you slang back at him?
Don't stand it. It would do him a lot of good.
I can't. I could have done it once.
But now I can't go back to it.
Last night, when I was wandering about, a girl spoke to me
and I tried to get back into the old way with her, but it was no use.
You told me, you know, that when a child is brought to a foreign country
it picks up the language in a few weeks and forgets its own.
Well, I am a child in your country.
I have forgotten my own language and can speak nothing but yours.
That's the real break-off with the corner of Tottenham Court Road.
Leaving Wimpole Street finishes it.
Oh, but you're coming back to Wimpole Street, aren't you?
You'll forgive Higgins?
Forgive? Will she bite George?
Let her go. Let her find out how she can get on without us.
She will relapse into the gutter in three weeks without me at her elbow.
He's incorrigible, Eliza.
You won't relapse, will you?
No, not now. Never again.
I have learnt my lesson.
I don't believe I could utter one of those old sounds if I tried.
Do you at all? What do you say to that?
Do a little?
Oh!
Ha! Just so!
How! How!
Victory! Victory!
Can you blame the girl?
Don't look at me like that, Eliza.
It ain't my fault. I've come into money.
You must have touched a millionaire this time, Dad.
I have, but I'm dressed something special today.
I'm going to St George's, Hanover Square.
Your stepmother is going to marry me!
You're going to let yourself down to marry that low, common woman?
He ought to, Eliza. Why has she changed her mind?
Intimidated, Governor. Intimidated!
Middle-class morality claims its victim.
Won't you put on your hat, Eliza, and come and see me turned off?
If the Colonel says I must, I...
I'll... I'll demean myself
and get insulted for my pains, like enough.
Don't be afraid. She never comes to words with anyone now, poor woman.
Respectability has broken all the spirit out of her.
Be kind to them, Eliza. Make the best of it.
Oh, well, just to show there's no ill feeling.
I'll be back in a moment.
I feel uncommon nervous about the ceremony, Colonel.
I wish you'd come and see me through it.
But you've been through it before, Matt.
You were married to Eliza's mother.
Who told you that, Colonel?
Well...
Nobody told me, but I concluded that...
No, no, no, that ain't the natural way, Colonel.
It's only the middle-class way.
My way was always the undeserving way.
But don't say nothing to Eliza. She don't know.
I always had a delicacy about telling her.
Quite right. We'll leave it so, if you don't mind.
And you'll come at the church, Colonel, and put me through straight?
With pleasure, as far as a bachelor can.
May I come, Mr Doolittle?
I should be very sorry to miss your wedding.
Oh, I should indeed be honoured by your condescension, ma'am.
And my poor old woman would take it as a tremendous compliment.
She's been very low, thinking of the happy days that are no more.
I'll order the carriage and get ready.
I shan't be more than 15 minutes.
Oh, Eliza, I'm going to the church to see your father married.
You had better come in the room with me.
Colonel Pickering can go on with the bridegroom.
Bridegroom?
Oh, what a word!
Makes a man realise his position somehow.
Before I go, Eliza, do forgive Higgins and come back to us.
I don't think Dad would allow me. Would you, Dad?
They played you off. Very cunning, Eliza.
Them two sportsmen.
If it had been only one of them, you could have nailed him.
But you see, there was two, and one of them chaperoned the other, as you might say.
It was artful of you, Colonel, but I bear you no malice.
I should have done the same myself.
I've been the victim of one woman after another all my life.
But don't grudge you two getting the better of Eliza.
I shan't interfere.
Right, it's time for us to go, Colonel.
So long, Henry.
See you in St George's, Eliza.
Do stay with us, Eliza.
Well, Eliza, you've had a bit of your own back, as you call it.
Have you had enough, and are you going to be reasonable,
or do you want any more?
You want me back only to pick up your slippers and put up with your tempers
and fetch and carry for you.
I haven't said I wanted you back at all.
No, indeed.
Then what are we talking about?
About you, not about me.
If you come back, I shall treat you just as I have always treated you.
I can't change my nature, and I don't intend to change my manners.
My manners are exactly the same as Colonel Pickering's.
That's not true. He treats a flower girl as if she was a duchess.
And I treat a duchess as if she was a flower girl.
I see. The same for everybody.
Just so.
Like father?
Without accepting the comparison at all points, Eliza,
it is quite true that your father is not a snob,
and that he will be quite at home in any station of life
to which his eccentric destiny may call him.
The great secret, Eliza, is not having bad manners or good manners
or any other particular sort of manners,
but having the same manner for all human souls.
In short, behaving as if you were in heaven,
where there are no third-class carriages,
and one soul is as good as another.
Amen. You are a born preacher.
The question is not whether I treat you rudely,
but whether you ever heard me treat anyone else better.
I don't care how you treat me.
I don't mind you swearing at me.
I don't mind a black eye.
I've had one before this, but I won't be passed over.
You talk about me as if I were a motor bus.
So you are a motor bus, all bounce and go,
and no consideration for anyone.
But I can do without you. Don't think I can't.
I know you can. I told you, you could.
Oh!
You never asked yourself, I suppose,
whether I could do without you.
Don't you try to get around me.
You'll have to do without me.
Oh, I can do without anybody.
I have my own soul, my own spark of divine fire.
But I shall miss you, Eliza.
I have learnt something from your idiotic notions.
I confess that, humbly and gratefully.
And I have grown accustomed to your voice and appearance.
I like them, rather.
Well, you have both of them on your gramophone
and in your book of photographs.
When you feel lonely without me, you can turn the machine on.
It's got no feelings to hurt.
I can't turn your soul on.
Leave me those feelings.
And you can take away the voice and the face.
They are not you.
Oh, you are a devil.
You can twist the heart in a girl
as easy as some could twist her arms to hurt her.
Mrs Pierce warned me.
Time and again she has wanted to leave you.
And you always got round her at the last minute.
And you don't care a bit for her.
And you don't care a bit for me.
I care for life, for humanity.
And you are a part of it that has come my way
and been built into my house.
What more can you or anyone ask?
I won't care for anybody that doesn't care for me.
Commercial principles, Eliza.
Like silly violets, isn't it?
Don't sneer at me. It's mean to sneer at me.
I have never sneered in my life.
Sneering doesn't become either the human face or the human soul.
I am expressing my righteous contempt for commercialism.
I don't and won't trade in affection.
You call me a brute because you couldn't buy a claim on me
by fetching my slippers and finding my spectacles.
You are a fool.
To think a woman fetching a man's slippers is a disgusting sight.
Did I ever fetch your slippers?
I think a good deal more of you for throwing them in my face.
No use slaving for me and then saying you want to be cared for.
Who cares for a slave?
If you come back, come back for the sake of good fellowship,
for you'll get nothing else.
You've had a thousand times as much out of me as I have out of you.
And if you dare to set up your little dog's tricks
by carrying slippers against my creation of a duchess, Eliza,
I'll slam the door in your silly face.
What did you do it for if you didn't care for me?
Why, because it was my job.
You never thought of the trouble it would make for me?
Would the world ever have been made
if its maker had been afraid of making trouble?
Making life means making trouble.
I'm no preacher. I don't notice things like that.
I notice that you don't notice me.
No, Eliza, you're an idiot.
I waste the treasures of my Miltonic mind by spreading them before you.
Once for all, understand that I go my way and do my work
without carrying tuppence what happens to either of us.
I am not intimidated like your father and your stepmother.
So you can come back or go to the devil, which you please.
What am I to come back for?
For the fun of it. That's why I took you on.
And you may throw me out tomorrow if I don't do everything you want me to?
Yes, and you may walk out tomorrow if I don't do everything you want me to.
And live with my stepmother?
Yes, or sell flowers.
Oh, if I only could go back to my flower basket,
I should be independent of both you and Father and all the world.
Why did you take my independence from me?
Why did I give it up?
I'm a slave now for all my fine clothes.
Not a bit.
I'll adopt you as my daughter and settle money on you, if you like.
Would you rather marry Pickering?
I wouldn't marry you if you asked me.
And you're nearer my age than what he is.
Than he is, not than what he is.
Oh, I'll talk as I like. You're not my teacher now.
I don't suppose Pickering would, though.
He's as confirmed an old bachelor as I am.
That's not what I want. And don't you think it.
I've always had chaps enough wanting me that way.
Freddy Hill writes to me twice and three times a day.
Sheets and sheets.
Damn his impudence.
He might do if he likes, poor lad.
And he does love me.
You have no right to encourage him.
Every girl has a right to be loved.
What? By fools like that?
Freddy's not a fool.
And if he's weak and poor and wants me,
maybe he'd make me happier than my betters
that bully me and don't want me.
Can he make anything of you? That's the point.
Perhaps I could make something of him.
But I never thought of us making anything of one another.
I never think of anything else.
I only want to be natural.
In short, you want me to be as infatuated about you as Freddy.
Is that it? No, I don't.
That's not the sort of feeling I want from you.
And don't you be too sure of yourself or of me.
I could have been a bad girl if I'd liked.
I've seen more of some things than you for all your learning.
Girls like me can drag gentlemen down to make love to them easy enough,
and they wish each other dead the next minute.
Of course they do.
Then what in thunder are we quarrelling about?
I want a little kindness.
I know I'm a common ignorant girl and you a book-learned gentleman,
but I'm not dirt under your feet.
What I'd done... What I did was not for the dresses and the taxis.
I did it because we were pleasant together and I came to care for you.
Not to want you to make love to me
and not forgetting the difference between us,
but more friendly-like.
Well, of course.
That's just how I feel.
And how Pickering feels.
Eliza, you're a fool.
That's not a proper answer to give me.
It's all you get until you stop being a common idiot.
If you're going to be a lady,
you'll have to give up feeling neglected
if the men you know don't spend half their time
snivelling over you and the other half giving you black eyes.
If you can't stand the coldness of my sort of life
and the strain of it, go back to the gutter.
Work till you are more a brute than a human being
and then cuddle and squabble and drink till you fall asleep.
Oh, it's a fine life, the life of the gutter.
It's real, it's warm, it's violent.
You can feel it through the thickest skin.
You can taste it and smell it without any training or any work.
Not like science and literature and classical music
and philosophy and art.
Ah...
You find me cold, unfeeling, selfish, don't you?
Very well.
Be off with you to the sort of people you like.
Marry some sentimental hog or other with lots of money
and a thick pair of lips to kiss you with
and a thick pair of boots to kick you with.
If you can't appreciate what you've got,
you'd better get what you can appreciate.
Oh, you are a cruel tyrant.
I can't talk to you. You turn everything against me.
I'm always in the wrong.
But you know very well all the time that you're nothing but a bully.
You know I can't go back to the gutter, as you call it,
and that I have no real friends in the world but you and the Colonel.
You know well I couldn't bear to live with a low common man after you two
and it's wicked and cruel of you to insult me by pretending I could.
You think I must go back to Wimpole Street
because I have nowhere else to go but fathers.
But don't you be too sure that you have me under your feet
to be trampled on and talked down.
I'll marry Freddy, I will, as soon as I'm able to support him.
Freddy? That young fool?
That poor devil who couldn't get a job as an errand boy,
even if he had the guts to try for it?
Do you not understand that I have made you consort for a king?
Freddy loves me. That makes him king enough for me.
I don't want him to work. He wasn't brought up to it as I was.
I'll go and be a teacher.
What will you teach in heaven's name?
What you taught me. I'll teach phonetics.
I'll offer myself as an assistant to that hairy-faced Hungarian.
What? That imposter? That humbug? That toadying ignoramus?
Teach him my methods, my discoveries.
You take one step in his direction and I'll wring your neck.
Do you hear?
Wring away? What do I care?
I knew you'd strike me someday.
Aha! Now I know how to deal with you.
What a fool I was not to think of it before.
You can't take away the knowledge you gave me.
You said I had a finer ear than you,
and I can be civil and kind to people which has more than you can.
Oh! Aha! That's done you, Henry Ickensley, yes?
Now I don't care that for your bullying and your big talk.
I'll advertise it in the papers
that your duchess is only a flower girl that you taught
and that she'll teach anybody to be a duchess just the same
in six months for a thousand guineas.
Oh, when I think of myself crawling under your feet
and being trampled on and called names
when all the time I had only to lift up my finger
to be as good as you, I could kick myself.
You damned impudent slut, you.
But it's better than snivelling,
better than fetching slippers and finding spectacles, isn't it?
By George, Eliza, I said I'd make a woman of you, and I have.
I like you like this.
Yes.
You can turn round and make up to me now that I'm not afraid of you
and couldn't do without you.
Of course I do, you little fool.
Five minutes ago you were like a millstone round my neck.
Now you're a tower of strength, a consort battleship.
You and I and Pickering will be three old bachelors together
instead of only two men and a silly girl.
The carriage is waiting, Eliza. Are you ready?
Quite. Is the Professor coming?
Certainly not. He can't behave himself in church.
He makes remarks out loud all the time on the clergyman's pronunciation.
Then I shall not see you again, Professor.
Goodbye.
Goodbye, dear.
Goodbye, Mother.
Oh, by the way, Eliza, order a ham and a Stilton cheese, will you?
And buy me a pair of reindeer gloves, number eights,
and a tie to match that new suit of mine.
That's Elon Binman's. You can choose the colour.
Number eights are too small for you if you want them lined with lamb's wool.
You have three new ties that you have forgotten in the drawer of your washstand.
Colonel Pickering prefers double Gloucester to Stilton.
I telephoned Mrs Pierce this morning not to forget the ham.
What you are to do without me I cannot imagine.
I'm afraid you've spoiled that girl, Henry.
I should be uneasy about you and her if she were less fond of Colonel Pickering.
Pickering? Nonsense!
She's going to marry Freddie!
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha!
Freddie!
In episode two of Pygmalion by George Bernard Shaw,
Higgins was played by Alastair McGowan,
Pickering by Hugh Fraser,
and Eliza by Morgana Robinson.
Doolittle was played by Al Murray,
Nepomuk by David Sturzica,
and Mrs Higgins by Sian Phillips.
Freddie Eynsford-Hill was played by Tom Forrester,
and a pal made by Charlotte Page.
The ambassador was John Dougal,
and the ambassador's wife, Sarah Ridgway.
Pygmalion was adopted and directed for radio by Emma Harding.